Guide to the Robert Henri Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1857-1929; Series II; 1.9; (5 boxes)
  - WRITINGS BY ROBERT HENRI
    - Art Spirit
      - Typescript carbons, corrected in Henri's hand (Box 21, Folder 495-510)
      - Notes by Henri on the arrangement of the book, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 511)
      - Text for the book jacket, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1923, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 512)
      - Review clippings, 1923-26 (Box 21, Folder 513-514)
      - Advertisements, 1923-24, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 515)
      - Dust jacket for the second impression (Box 22, Folder 516)
        Lacking front cover
      - Library of Congress catalog card, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 517)
    - Writings Related to Teaching
      Composition Talks
      - Nos. 2-6, typescript carbon, corrected, 1910, n.d.
      - Nos. 7-11, typescript carbon, corrected, 1910 (Box 22, Folder 519)
      - Nos. 12-13, typescript carbon, corrected, 1911 (Box 22, Folder 520)
      - Nos. 17-19, typescript carbon, corrected, 1911 (Box 22, Folder 521)
      - Criticisms of Class Artwork
        - Typescript carbon, corrected, 1907 (Box 22, Folder 522)
        - Typescript carbon, corrected, 1909 (Box 22, Folder 523)
        - Typescript carbon, corrected, 1910 (Box 22, Folder 524-526)
        - Typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 527)
      - Class Notes
        - Holograph and typescript, corrected (Box 22, Folder 528-530)
        - Taken by Clara Greenleaf Perry, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 22, Folder 531)
      - Letters to the Class
        - Holograph and typescript, corrected, 1915 (Box 22, Folder 532)
        - Typescript and holograph, corrected, 1917, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 533)
    - Other Writings
      - "'The Big Exhibition' The Artist and the Public" draft, holograph carbon, 1917 (Box 23, Folder 534)
      - Essay on Eugene Speicher, holograph and holograph carbon (Box 23, Folder 535)
      - Forum Exhibition article, holograph drafts, 1916 Feb (Box 23, Folder 536)
      - List of paintings and framing instructions [?] (Box 23, Folder 537)
      - Notebook with miscellaneous notes on art, holograph, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 538)
      - Notes made at time of Charcoal Club, holograph, 1893 (Box 23, Folder 539)
      - Outline for projected autobiography, covering years 1888-1901, holograph, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 540)
      - "On Art" notebook, holograph, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 541)
      - Résumés, typescript and typescript carbon, 1920-25 (Box 23, Folder 542)
      - Statement regarding his business relations with the New York School of Art, holograph, [1908 Jan] (Box 23, Folder 543)
      - Writings related to MacDowell Club exhibitions, holograph, 1911-17, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 544-545)
      - Miscellaneous notes in shorthand, 1928, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 546)
        Including possible journal entries, and draft of a letter
      - Fragments, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 547)
  - WRITINGS BY OTHERS
    - Violet Organ
      Journal of Student Days
      - Arranged in draft order
      - "Student Days of Robert Henri" typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 548)
        Covering Jan 26 1890 to Nov 14 1890, with gaps
      - "Robert Henri _ Journal of Student Days" typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 549)
        Covering Jan 12 1890 to Oct 17 1890, with gaps
      - "Henri Speaks for Himself" typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 550)
        Covering Jan 17 1890 to Jan 30 1891, with gaps
      - "Robert Henri _ Journal of Student Days" typescript and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 23, Folder 551-553)
        Covering Jan 30 1889 to Sep 12 1891, with gaps
      - "Robert Henri _ Journal of Student Days" typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 554-555)
        Covering Oct 16 1886 to Sep 25 1891, with gaps
      - "Henri Speaks for Himself" typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 556)
        Covering Jan 21 1891 to Mar 22, 1891
      - Miscellaneous pages, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 557)
      - Notes by Violet Organ while working on biography of Henri, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 23, Folder 558)
      - Journal, 1925 Jul-Sep (Box 24, Folder 559)
      - Miscellaneous fiction scenes and notes (Box 24, Folder 560-561)
      - Notes on Henri and the correspondence, [1907], n.d. (Box 24, Folder 562)
    - Others
      - Barouch Portrait, typescript, 1920 Jun (Box 24, Folder 563)
      - Bellows, George. Manuscript about Henri's "Ideal Scheme of Exhibitions" holograph, corrected, [1914] (Box 24, Folder 564)
      - Critiques of Henri's work by Adam and Prinet, autograph manuscript (Box 24, Folder 565)
      - Henri, Linda Craige. Five holograph poems (Box 24, Folder 566)
      - Interview between Margery Ryerson and ? Geyer, incomplete typescript (Box 24, Folder 567)
      - Longstaff. Notes on Valasques [Velázquez] in letter to [Allen?] Tucker, 1890 Jun 15 (Box 24, Folder 568)
      - Sloan, John. "We had a little setter dog" holograph poem, n.d.
        See: Box 10, folder 241
      - Spaulding, George F. Ballad. Holograph in Henri's hand (Box 24, Folder 569)
      - Speicher, Eugene. Foreword to a work on George Bellows, typescript, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 570)
      - "Notes on Lecture by Maximilian Toch," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 571)
      - Unidentified. "The Artist's League" typescript mimeograph, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 572)
      - Unidentified. "Full bright are the rays around the bridal pair playing" holograph, signed by M, Kanawha, Va., 1857 Jul 13 (Box 24, Folder 573)
      - Unidentified. List of books on art, typescript, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 574)
      - Unidentified. List of pictures in order in which they appear in the Cecil book, typescript, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 575)
      - Unidentified. Notes on art, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 576)
      - Compilation of compositions of school girls who heard Henri lecture in Toledo, Ohio, 1911 (Box 24, Folder 577)
- Art Notebooks and Sketches, 1904-1928; Series III; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  Series III, Art Notebooks and Sketches, is organized into two subseries: Art Notebooks and Sketches.
  - ART NOTEBOOKS
    - Artists Pigments notebook I, 1913-26, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 578-590)
    - Artists Pigments notebook II, 1916-19 (Box 25, Folder 591-596)
    - Artists Pigments draft, 1922 Jun (Box 25, Folder 597)
    - Artists Pigments digest, holograph and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 25, Folder 598)
    - "Paint" notebook with diagrams of color palettes and chords, and notes on the brush stroke, color, and backgrounds (Box 26, Folder 599)
    - Paint 3 notebook, 1919-20 (Box 26, Folder 600-605)
    - Paint 4 notebook, 1921 (Box 26, Folder 606)
    - Paint 5 notebook, 1926-28 (Box 26, Folder 607)
    - Draft of essay about Jay Hambidge's "Whirling Square" theory, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 608)
      See also: Oversize, box 32, folder 704
    - Notebooks studying Jay Hambidge's "Whirling Square" theory, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 609)
      See also: Oversize, box 32, folder 705, and box 33, folder 723
    - Notebook with notes on easels and canvas carriers and bylaws for an unidentified art society (Box 26, Folder 610)
    - Notebook with notes on art with three sketches in pen and ink and in pencil (Box 26, Folder 611)
  - SKETCHES
    - Sketch of a boy with two studies of heads, unsigned, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 612)
    - Sketch of a man holding a piece of paper, unsigned, with RH blind embossed on paper (Box 26, Folder 612a)
    - Sketch of a three men in a sidecar, unsigned, n.d. (Box 26, Folder 613)
    - Sketch of a girl on Achill Island, unsigned (Box 26, Folder 614)
    - Sloan, John. Sketch of a gargoyle flying, [1907 Dec]
      See: Box 10, folder 239
    - Sloan, John. Sketch of Henri? in front of an easel, [1904]
    - Yeats, John Butler. Sketch of a skeleton with a woman's face and cupid in the background, [1921]
      See: Box 11, folder 277
- Family Papers, 1869-1923; Series IV; 0.4; (1 box)
  Series IV, Family Papers, is arranged in chronological order; undated material filed at the end.
  - Silhouettes of Mr. and Mrs. Richard H. Lee (Box 27, Folder 615)
  - Catalogue of the Chickering Classical and Scientific Institute Cincinnati, O. (Box 27, Folder 616)
    Robert H. Cozad listed in the Intermediate Department, A Grade
  - Notebook belonging to Richard H. Lee (?) containing phrenological studies of the family, copies of correspondence relating to cases, accounts, and short diary entries, 1878-1923 (Box 27, Folder 617)
  - Phrenological study of Robert Henri, 1878 Jan 9 (Box 27, Folder 618)
    Study is the same as the one appearing in the notebook in folder above
  - Looseleaf pages from notebook containing miscellaneous accounts, journal entries and other notes kept by Mr. and Mrs. Richard H. Lee, 1879-1916, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 619)
  - Receipts for sale of land in Cozaddale (Ohio) to Thomas Jones, 1882 May (Box 27, Folder 620)
  - Power of attorney from Theresa G. Cozad to John N. Dryden to prosecute suits on her behalf for purpose of recovering land in Nebraska, 1911 Apr (Box 27, Folder 621)
  - Bill of Fare of the St. Dennis Restaurant. S. E. Gatewood, Proprietor, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 622)
  - Deposition of the proprietor of the Hundredth Meridian newspaper in a case involving John Jackson Cozad (Box 27, Folder 623)
  - Note about a legal question, possibly written by Richard H. Lee, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 624)
  - Notes recording land transactions in Cozad, Nebraska (Box 27, Folder 625)
  - Genealogical notes, n.d. (Box 27, Folder 626)
- Printed Material, 1893-1958; Series V; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Series V, Printed Material, is organized into three subseries: Clippings, Periodicals, and Other Printed Material. Within the subseries, the material is arranged alphabetically.
  - CLIPPINGS
    - "The 'Big Exhibition', The Artist and the Public" The Touchstone Vol. 1, No. 2, 1917 Jun (Box 28, Folder 627)
    - "An Ideal Exhibition Scheme" Arts & Decoration Vol. 5, No. 2, 1914 Dec (Box 28, Folder 628)
    - Letter to the Editor of Public Ledger, 1916 Apr 28 (Box 28, Folder 629)
    - "Mary Rogers--Sister and Artist" introduction The International Studio Vol. 73, No. 290, 1921 May (Box 28, Folder 630)
    - "My People:" The Craftsman Vol. 27, No. 5, 1915 Feb (Box 28, Folder 631)
    - "The New York Exhibition of Independent Artists" The Craftsman Vol. 18, No. 2 (Box 28, Folder 632)
    - "Progress in Our National Art Must Spring from the Development of Individuality of Ideas and Freedom of Expression: A Suggestion for a New Art School" The Craftsman Vol. 15, No. 4, 1909 Jan (Box 28, Folder 633-634)
    - "What About Art in America" Arts & Decoration Vol. 24, No. 1, 1925 Nov
      See: Oversize, box 32, folder 706
    - Untitled articles in The Conservator, 1915, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 635)
      See also: Oversize, box 32, folder 707
    - Clippings about Henri, [1900-14] (Box 28, Folder 636-642)
      See also: Oversize, box 32, folder 708
    - Clippings about Henri, [1915-58], n.d. (Box 29, Folder 643-653)
      See also: Oversize, box 32, folder 709
    - Clippings about art and artists, [1896-1969], n.d. (Box 29, Folder 654-656)
    - Clippings about friends of Henri, [1922], n.d. (Box 29, Folder 657)
  - PERIODICALS
    - The Art Digest Vol 8, No. 20, 1934 Sep 1 (Box 29, Folder 658)
    - The Art Digest Vol. 18, No. 14, 1944 Apr 15 (Box 29, Folder 659)
    - The Arts Vol. 1, No. 1, 1920 Dec 4 (Box 29, Folder 660)
    - Arts Digest Vol. 29, No. 13, 1955 Apr 1 (Box 29, Folder 661)
    - International Studio Vol. 75, No. 299, 1922 Mar (Box 29, Folder 662)
  - OTHER PRINTED MATERIAL
    - Avalon Summer Assembly course catalog, 1893 (Box 30, Folder 663)
    - Butler, Howard Russell. Separately printed letter to the Editor of the New York Times, 1929 Mar 29 (Box 30, Folder 664)
    - Exhibition catalogues featuring Henri's work, 1897-1954, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 665-669)
    - Exhibition invitations, 1902-65, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 670)
    - George Bellows exhibition catalogue, [1959] (Box 30, Folder 671)
    - Henri School of Art prospectus, [1908?] (Box 30, Folder 672)
    - MacDowell Club of New York exhibition prospectuses, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 673)
    - New York School of Art summer tour prospectuses, 1906-07 (Box 30, Folder 674)
    - Philadelphia School of Design for Women course catalog, 1893 (Box 30, Folder 675)
    - Plates from antiquarian booksellers' catalogues, n.d. (Box 30, Folder 676)
    - Programme of the Special Performance of Lord Dundreary Given by Mr. Sothern and his Company..., 1915 (Box 30, Folder 677)
      Illustrated by Childe Hassam, George Bellows, John Sloan, W. Glackens
    - Newspaper confetti gathered during celebration of surrender of Germany, 1918 Nov (Box 30, Folder 678)
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets, 1941, 1954 (Box 30, Folder 679)
- Photographs, 1886-1916; Series VI; 0.2; (1 box)
  Series VI, Photographs is organized into four subseries: Robert Henri and Others, Other People, Artwork, and Places.
  - ROBERT HENRI AND OTHERS
    - Robert Henri, [1906], n.d. (Box 31, Folder 680-681)
      See also: Oversize, box 32, folder 710
      Includes photograph of Henri in front of train ticket booklet
    - Henri's apartment in Paris, ca. 1888-89 (Box 31, Folder 682)
      One image of Henri scrubbing dishes
    - Friends at Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts (group of ten), [1887] (Box 31, Folder 683)
      Names noted on back: Robert Henri, E. R. Coleman, Willman, E. O. Wingert, E. W. Redfield, A. Calder, W. Haefeker, W. E. Parker, C. S. Williamson, Chas. Grafly
    - Group photograph of the students at the Académie Julian, Paris, [1890 Dec] (Box 31, Folder 684)
    - Portrait of players in "Grand Operatic Tragedy", ca. 1892
      See: Oversize, box 32, folder 711
      Names noted at bottom of mat: Grafly, Henri, Breckenridge, Parker, Paynter, Williamson, Coleman
    - Summer Assembly, Avalon, New Jersey class painting in a meadow, [1893 Jul] (Box 31, Folder 685)
    - Charcoal Club: "Gypsy" baptising the Club at opening, [1893] (Box 31, Folder 686)
      Names noted at bottom of mat: Grenger, W. Glackens, Sunstrum, Rudy, Hicks, Gosewitz, Sloan, Henri, Young, Warden, Swazye, Harley
    - Henri and others at a studio [his?], [1893] (Box 31, Folder 687)
      Names noted on back of one: Chas. Grafly, Everett ?, Koopman, W. Glackens, Benj. Fox, Sam'l Hall, John Sloan, ? Smith, R. Henri, Pfortzer, Everett Shinn. On the second, the names John Sloan, Karl Fast, R. Henri
    - Henri posing in front of "Woman in Manteau", [1898?]
      See: Oversize, box 32, folder 712
    - New York Art School night class group portrait, [1904 Mar]
      See: Oversize, box 32, folder 713
      Names noted at bottom of mat: Scovil, Chaffee, Ament, Slaymaker, Barrett, Greves, Spinchorn, Kent, Harper, Adams, Daugherty, Hopper, Cedrequist, Chatterton, Avison, Main, Clemens, Kalbe, Baumgardner, Coleman, Wheeler, R. Henri, Guy du Bois, Fallet, Golz
    - New York Art School night class group portrait, [1904 Apr]
      See: Oversize, box 32, folder 714
    - New York Art School night class group portrait, [1904 May]
      See: Oversize, box 32, folder 715
      Names noted at bottom of mat: Carter, Koopman, Pach, Williams, Strusss, Hatch, Tschenk, Cedrequist, Invernizzi, Dreiser, Harting, Winn, Bohnen, Boss, Fallert, Sterett, Levy, Henri, Van Sloan, Brock, Freidman
    - Art Students League group portrait, [1916 Mar]
      See: Oversize, box 32, folder 716
    - Group portrait, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 688)
      Names noted at bottom: Jongers, Francis Jones, Ben Foster, Henri, I. Wiles, Will Low, Barse, K. Cox, Bolton Jones, Kost
    - Henri and John Sloan and another man (Box 31, Folder 689)
    - Henri and unidentified woman (Box 31, Folder 690)
    - Group portraits of unidentified club during a party, n.d.
      See: Oversize, box 32, folders 717-718
  - OTHER PEOPLE
    - Archbishop of Canterbury and Bishop Potter, [1904]
      See: Oversize, box 32, folder 719
    - Bellows, George and Randall Davey, [1914 Aug] (Box 31, Folder 691)
    - Bellows, George, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 692)
    - Charles Grafly with bicycle, ca. 1886
      See: Oversize, box 32, folder 720
    - William Faversham and his two sons (Box 31, Folder 693)
    - Johnson, [W. J. Jr.?], [1914 Mar] (Box 31, Folder 694)
    - Group of seven unidentified men, sent with compliments of Charles Grafly, n.d.
      See: Oversize, box 32, folder 721
  - ARTWORK
    - Art Institute of Chicago, interior view, [1905 Nov] (Box 31, Folder 695)
      Showing "Young Woman in Black" on the far wall
    - "Young Woman in Black" by Henri, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 696)
    - Postcard of painting by Berthe Morisot, "Fillette au panier", n.d. (Box 31, Folder 697)
    - Postcards (2) of painting by F. J. Van Slauer, [1905 Jan 20] (Box 31, Folder 698)
  - PLACES
    - Atlantic City buildings on the beach, [1896 Jul 17]
      See: Oversize, box 32, folder 722
    - Postcards of Gramercy Park, n.d. (Box 31, Folder 699)
    - Postcard of the beach at Ostend (Box 31, Folder 700)
- Oversize, 3.5; (2 boxes)
  Oversize contains material from Series I-III, V-VI, arranged in box order.
  - "F" general (from Series I), 1921 Sep 8 (Box 32, Folder 701)
  - McPherson, John C. (from Series I), 1913 (Box 32, Folder 702)
  - Class notes, holograph and typescript, corrected (from Series II) (Box 32, Folder 703)
  - Draft of essay about Jay Hambidge's "Whirling Square" theory (from Series III), n.d. (Box 32, Folder 704)
  - Notebook studying Jay Hambidge's "Whirling Square" theory (from Series III), n.d. (Box 32, Folder 705)
  - "What About Art in America" Arts & Decoration Vol. 24, No. 1 (from Series V) (Box 32, Folder 706)
  - Untitled articles in The Conservator (from Series V), 1915, n.d. (Box 32, Folder 707)
  - Clippings about Henri (from Series V), 1906 (Box 32, Folder 708)
  - Clippings about Henri (from Series V), 1923 (Box 32, Folder 709)
  - Robert Henri (from Series VI), n.d. (Box 32, Folder 710)
  - Portrait of players in "Grand Operatic Tragedy" (from Series VI), ca. 1892 (Box 32, Folder 711)
  - Henri posing in front of "Woman in Manteau" (from Series VI), [1898?] (Box 32, Folder 712)
  - New York Art School night class group portrait (from Series VI), [1904 Mar] (Box 32, Folder 713)
  - New York Art School night class group portrait (from Series VI), [1904 Apr] (Box 32, Folder 714)
  - New York Art School night class group portrait (from Series VI), [1904 May] (Box 32, Folder 715)
  - Art Students League group portrait (from Series VI), [1916 Mar] (Box 32, Folder 716)
  - Group portraits of unidentified club during a party (from Series VI), n.d. (Box 32, Folder 717-718)
  - Archbishop of Canterbury and Bishop Potter (from Series VI), [1904] (Box 32, Folder 719)
  - Charles Grafly with bicycle (from Series VI), ca. 1886 (Box 32, Folder 720)
  - Group of seven unidentified men, sent with compliments of Charles Grafly (from Series VI), n.d. (Box 32, Folder 721)
  - Atlantic City buildings on the beach (from Series VI), [1896 Jul 17] (Box 32, Folder 722)
  - Notebook studying Jay Hambidge's "Whirling Square" theory (from Series III), n.d. (Box 33, Folder 723)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 34-35, Restricted Fragile Papers, contains fragile originals. The material is arranged in folder order and may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies have been placed in the main files for reference use.
  - Box 2, folder 32 (Box 34, Folder 724)
  - Box 5, folder 123 (Box 34, Folder 725)
  - Box 6, folders 141, 148 (Box 34, Folder 726)
  - Box 7, folder 167 (Box 34, Folder 727)
  - Box 9, folders 218-219 (Box 34, Folder 728)
  - Box 17, folder 419 (Box 34, Folder 729)
  - Box 21, folders 513-514 (Box 34, Folder 730-732)
  - Box 23, folder 534 (Box 34, Folder 733)
  - Box 28, folders 629, 636-642 (Box 34, Folder 734-740)
  - Box 29, folders 643-657 (Box 34, Folder 741-751)
  - Box 28, folders 636-642 (Box 35, Folder 752)
  - Box 29, folders 643-653 (Box 35, Folder 752)